Guide to the Edith Kramer Papers MC.215
New York University Archives
- Series V: Artwork, 1916-2000; 8.75 Linear Feet In 52 custom portfolios, 6 oversize flat boxes, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 4 flat file folders, and 14 large artworks.
  - Sub-Series B: Artwork Created During Art Therapy, 1951-2000
    1 "MS#1418 - Wiltwyck School for Boys Records," Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, accessed October 20, 2023, https://findingaids.library.columbia.edu/ead/nnc-rb/ldpd_6262245#summary
    - [angel and devil], ca. 1951-1957
      18 x 22 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished.
      Historical
      This artwork was created at Wiltyck School for Boys between 1951 and 1957.
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Do not remove hinges until 2099; they conceal private health information.
    - [birds], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 3)
      24 1/2 x 36 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [children, sun, and moon], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 1)
      24 x 36 inches, matte opaque paint on red paper, varnished.
    - [creature with antennae], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      12 9/16 x 14 7/16 inches. transparent and opaque paints on paper, varnished
    - [creature], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 5L)
      18 x 23 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books.
    - [figure with large bottle], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 2R)
      Biographical / Historical
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [gallows], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 5L)
      24 x 18 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [guillotine], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 4L)
      Reproduced in: Kramer, Edith, 1958. Art Therapy in a Children's Community. Springield, Ill.: Thomas; and Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books.
    - [injured head], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 3L)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished.
    - [injured whale], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 1R)
      Do not alter the position of window mat before 2099; it conceals private health information.
    - [king with large crown], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 1R)
      19 3/8 x 25 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
      Do not remove patch on recto until 2099; it conceals private health information.
    - [ocean scene], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 3R)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - [painting of sun with red mouth and blue eyes], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 6R)
    - [portrait of figure in Native American headdress], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      12 x 9 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [portrait of two faces], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 2L)
      18 x 24 inches, two 8.5 x 11 inch pieces of paper (one reproduction and one graphite), mounted with staples
      Do not alter the position of window mat until 2099; it conceals private health information.
    - [portrait with black eye], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 4R)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint and charcoal on paper, varnished
      Do not change window mat location or remove hinges until 2099; they conceal private health information.
    - [ships at sea], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 4)
      32 x 40 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
      Do not remove hinges or patch on recto until 2099; they conceal private health information.
    - [smoking man], ca. 1951-1957
      17 1/4 x 13 1/2 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - [snowflake with two red suns], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      9 x 14 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [sun with teeth], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 5R)
      19 3/4 x 25 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
      Reproduced in: Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books; and Kramer, Edith. 2000a. Art as Therapy: Collected Papers. London; Philadelphia: Jessica Kingsley Publishers.
    - [whale dying], ca. 1951-1957
      14 x 20 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
      Do not remove hinges or window mat until 2099; they conceal personal health information.
    - Brooding Witch Doctor, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 6R)
      18 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on Bristol board, varnished
    - Dancing Beauty and Dancing Colt, or Family of Horses, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 6L)
      Reproduced in: Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books.
    - Devil, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 4R)
      23 3/4 x 18 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - Egyptian Princess, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 5)
      24 x 35 1/2inches, matte opaque paint on brown paper, varnished
    - Grinning Witch Doctor, 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 5R)
      18 1/4 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on Bristol board, varnished
    - Hawk Chasing Rabbitt -11 Year Old or Rabbit Pursued by Vulture, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 1L)
      18 x 24 inches, charcoal on paper, varnished
    - Horse Against Rider, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 3L)
      24 1/4 x 18 1/4 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - Indian Chief, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 7)
      36 1/8 x 24 1/4 inches, matte opaque paint on Bristol board, varnished
    - King, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 3R)
    - Mare and Colt, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Moby Dick, The White Whale, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 2)
      18 x 48 inches, matte opaque paint on illustration board, varnished
    - Monster, Matthew, 13 years old, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 2L)
      30 x 27 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, mounted to Mastonite, varnished
    - City Streets, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      6 1/8 x 8 3/4 inches, graphite on paper, varnished
      Reproduced in: Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books; and Art Therapy in a Children's community
    - Playful Horses, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 7L)
    - Playground Sketches, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Two (2) 10 x 7 1/2 inches, graphite on paper, varnished
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith, 1958. Art Therapy in a Children's Community. Springield, Ill.: Thomas.
      Do not reposition the window mat until 2099; it conceals private health information.
    - Radiant Sun, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 4R)
      17 1/2 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - Spanish Dancer, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 8)
      24 x 36 inches, matte opaque paint on Bristol board, varnished
    - The Art Teacher, ca. 1951-1957 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      13 1/4 x 11 inches, graphite on paper, varnished
    - The Art Teacher, 10 1/2 year, ca. 1951-1957
      18 x 12 inches, charcoal on paper, varnished
      Do not remove patch on recto or hinges until 2099; they conceal private health information.
    - The Eskimo, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 4L)
      19 x 22 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - The Mother, 11 years old, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 5R)
    - Wedding, ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 6)
      24 x 36 inches, matte opaque paint on violet paper, varnished
    - [diptych of candles], ca. 1951-1957 (Flat-file-folder 2L)
      18 x 12 inches each, matte opaque paint on black paper, varnished.
    - [child with pink petals], ca. 1951-2000 (Flat-file-folder 3L)
      Artwork was likely created by Edith Kramer as a demostration work.
    - [owl with hare], ca. 1951-2000 (Flat-file-folder 1R)
      24 x 18 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - [pond in forest with two figures], ca. 1951-2000 (Flat-file-folder 4L)
      18 1/4 x 24 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - Prisoner by William "Butch" Bosket, ca. 1953-1957 (Flat-file-folder 2)
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books; and with artist's identify reveal in Butterfield, Fox. 1995. All God's Children: The Bosket Family and the American Tradition of Violence. New York: Knopf: Distributed by Random House.
    - Young Man with Switchblade by William "Butch" Bosket, 1957 (Flat-file-folder 1)
      36 x 47 1/2 inches, matte opaque paint on paper mounted to Masonite, varnished
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith. 1972. Art as Therapy with Children. New York, Schocken Books; and with artist's identify revealed in Butterfield, Fox. 1995. All God's Children: The Bosket Family and the American Tradition of Violence. New York: Knopf: Distributed by Random House.
    - [drawing of Edith Kramer with a child drawing in the background], ca. 1958-1971 (Flat-file-folder 5L)
      This artwork was created by art therapy receipent "Angel" as part of an autobiography.
      18 x 24 inches, charcoal on paper varnished
      Do not reposition window mat until 2099; it conceals private health information.
    - [portrait of a boy with a speech bubble], ca. 1958-1971 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      14 1/8 x 22 inches
    - My art teacher, Edith Kramer, ca. 1958-1971 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      12 1/2 x 9 1/2 inches
      Do not reposition of window mat until 2099; it conceals private health information.
    - [figure with oversized muscles], 1958-1972 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - [figure with torch and baby in basket], ca. 1958-1971 (Box 17, Folder 3)
      12 x 18 inches, charcoal on paper, varnished
    - Hercunles, ca. 1958-1979
      This artwork is titled "Hercunles" but it appears to be a depiction of Hercules.
      12 x 18 inches, charcoal on paper
      Do not remove tape; it conceals private health information and was applied by Edith Kramer.
    - [portrait of Edith Kramer], ca. 1958-1979 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      This artwork created by art therapy receipent "Angel" as part of an autobiography.
      19 x 13 inches, black matte opaque paint on paper, varnished.
    - [color squiggles], ca. 1958-1979 (Flat-file-folder 7L)
      16 3/4 x 29 1/2 inches
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith. 1979. Childhood and Art Therapy: Notes on Theory and Application, edited by Laurie Wilson. New York: Schocken Books.
    - [painting of a house], ca. 1958-1979 (Flat-file-folder 2R)
      26 1/2 x 21 7/8 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
      Reproduced in Kramer, Edith (1979) Childhood and Art Therapy: Notes on Theory and Application by Edith Kramer, Schoken.
      Do not remove hinges until 2099; they conceals private health information.
    - Sunset Over The Bronx, ca. 1958-1979 (Flat-file-folder 2L)
      18 x 24 inches, opaque paint on colored paper, varnished
    - [bombing of an airfield], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      13 3/4 x 17 inches, crayon on paper
    - [cartoon characters], ca. 1958-2000 (Flat-file-folder 3R)
    - [colorful diagonal lines], 1958-2000 (Flat-file-folder 2R)
      19 3/4 x 26 inches, matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [crowd], ca. 1958-2000 (Flat-file-folder 1L)
      18 7/8 x 25 inches, black porous point pen on paper
    - [outdoor concert], ca. 1958-2000 (Flat-file-folder 1)
    - [two figures one with horns], 1958-2000 (Flat-file-folder 1L)
      Black matte opaque paint on paper, varnished
    - [underwater scene, figure with shark], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 15, Folder 5)
      9 x 12 inches, matte opaque paint on paper
    - [untitled cityscape with sun drawing], ca. 1958-2000 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      18 x 12 inches, crayon on paper
    - [colorful lines], ca. 1958-2000 (Flat-file-folder 6L)
      24 x 18 inches, crayon on paper
    - [portrait with braids and headdress], ca. 1951-1957 (Box 17, Folder 2)
      18 x 12 inches, graphite with matte opaque paint on paper